<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Report on The TechGlider</title>
    <link>https://techglider.github.io/tags/report/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Report on The TechGlider</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://techglider.github.io/tags/report/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Reason about Correctness of Programs Designed for Non-Volatile Memory?</title>
      <link>https://techglider.github.io/update/how-to-reason-about-correctness-of-programs-designed-for-non-volatile-memory/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jun 2017 21:54:56 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://techglider.github.io/update/how-to-reason-about-correctness-of-programs-designed-for-non-volatile-memory/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I recently graduated with a &lt;a href=&#34;https://cs.brown.edu/degrees/masters/&#34;&gt;master&amp;rsquo;s degree&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&#34;https://cs.brown.edu&#34;&gt;Computer Science&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.brown.edu&#34;&gt;Brown University&lt;/a&gt;. My project report that documents the work I did over the last one year is now available on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cs.brown.edu/research/pubs/theses/masters/&#34;&gt;Brown CS website&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&#34;https://cs.brown.edu/research/pubs/theses/masters/2017/singhal.kartik.pdf&#34;&gt;https://cs.brown.edu/research/pubs/theses/masters/2017/singhal.kartik.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am making a copy available here as well: &lt;a href=&#34;https://techglider.github.io/kartik-scm-report.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditional storage stack necessitates a separate data format for the persistence of in-memory data structures, requires additional code for conversion to that data format and wastes a lot of CPU time. Upcoming byte-addressable non-volatile memory (NVM) technologies such as memristors or phase change memory offer an opportunity to rethink how code interacts with persistent data. Researchers have come up with a variety of programming models to make effective use of NVM but, unfortunately, it is considered hard to reason about the safety properties provided by these models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this report, we look at existing work in a somewhat related field of formal reasoning about the correctness of concurrent software and discuss whether those techniques can be applied to software designed for NVM or persistent memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also document our design of a concurrent graph data structure for non-volatile memory which offers crash-resilience with the help of Atlas programming model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>