<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Congestion Control on The TechGlider</title>
    <link>https://techglider.github.io/tags/congestion-control/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Congestion Control on The TechGlider</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://techglider.github.io/tags/congestion-control/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>BBR: Congestion-based Congestion Control</title>
      <link>https://techglider.github.io/review/bbr-congestion-based-congestion-control/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2017 08:32:13 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://techglider.github.io/review/bbr-congestion-based-congestion-control/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;paper-title&#34;&gt;Paper Title&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BBR: Congestion-based Congestion Control&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;author-s&#34;&gt;Author(s)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neal Cardwell, Yuchung Cheng, C. Stephen Gunn, Soheil Hassas Yeganeh, Van Jacobson&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;date&#34;&gt;Date&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;October 2016. Appeared in both:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;September-October 2016. ACM Queue - Network Congestion Vol. 14 No. 5&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 2017. Communications of the ACM Volume 60 Issue 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;doi-authoritative-link-to-paper&#34;&gt;DOI/Authoritative Link to Paper&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ACM Queue: &lt;a href=&#34;http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=3022184&#34;&gt;doi:10.1145/3012426.3022184&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CACM: &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1145/3009824&#34;&gt;doi:10.1145/3009824&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://research.google.com/pubs/pub45646.html&#34;&gt;Listing on Research at Google&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;novel-idea-main-result-s&#34;&gt;Novel Idea / Main Result(s)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper describes how by identifying the core parameters in congestion control &amp;ndash; propagation time of the physical medium and bottleneck bandwidth &amp;ndash; the authors were able to come up with a new congestion control mechanism (BBR) that is refreshingly simple and performs better in most cases in both bandwidths and latency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;impact&#34;&gt;Impact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After reading the &lt;a href=&#34;https://techglider.github.io/review/analysis-and-simulation-of-a-fair-queueing-algorithm/&#34;&gt;last&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://techglider.github.io/review/flow-rate-fairness-dismantling-a-religion/&#34;&gt;two&lt;/a&gt; papers, I was surprised how advanced math and non-intuitive solutions had taken over the world of network management at Internet scale. This paper&amp;rsquo;s attempt to go to the very bottom of the problem by relooking at Kleinrock&amp;rsquo;s formal model of congestion and utilizing modern control theory to come up with a simple state machine as a solution is both refreshing and relaxing. The experiments performed at the Google scale over a span of services and time periods validate their reasoning and ideas. I feel comfortable to say that this paper&amp;rsquo;s contributions hold huge potential for the future of Internet architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;evidence&#34;&gt;Evidence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors have used a variety of analyses to present convincing arguments to validate their proposal &amp;ndash; simple intuitive reasoning about the problem of congestion conforming to (classical?) research in the formal theory of communications (Kleinrock); mathematical but fairly intuitive linear programming analysis; multiple comparisons with the behavior of a previous well-optimized TCP implementation (CUBIC) and finally and perhaps most importantly experiments done on both Google&amp;rsquo;s WAN and YouTube which provide real-world insights and strong evidence in their favor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reproducibility&#34;&gt;Reproducibility&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes! The implementation is merged in Linux kernel version 4.9.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;question&#34;&gt;Question&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really liked how, once again, the difference between a spec (TCP) and its various implementations is illustrated in this paper and how end-to-end argument is still relevant even after we have seen so many violations in existing Internet infrastructure. I would like to brainstorm about where else rethinking old ideas from scratch and reducing the problems to their very core has a potential of significant improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;criticism&#34;&gt;Criticism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would have loved to see some graphs with mix flows of some existing TCP implementation and their interaction with BBR flows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ideas-for-further-work&#34;&gt;Ideas for further work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given how this paper reduced the problem of congestion control to its fundamental core (RTprop and BtlBw) and is designed to stabilize while keeping the queues empty, I am wondering how many complicated queue management solutions (such as the one proposed in the previous paper we read from Briscoe) may not be required anymore and perhaps should be reevaluated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Review Template Credits:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://cs.brown.edu/courses/csci2950-u/s14/review.html&#34;&gt;Prof. Rodrigo Fonseca&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flow Rate Fairness: Dismantling a Religion</title>
      <link>https://techglider.github.io/review/flow-rate-fairness-dismantling-a-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2017 14:05:49 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://techglider.github.io/review/flow-rate-fairness-dismantling-a-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;paper-title&#34;&gt;Paper Title&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flow Rate Fairness: Dismantling a Religion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;author-s&#34;&gt;Author(s)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bob Briscoe&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;date&#34;&gt;Date&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;March 2007. ACM SIGCOMM Computer Communication Review, Volume 37 Issue 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;doi-authoritative-link-to-paper&#34;&gt;DOI/Authoritative Link to Paper&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1145/1232919.1232926&#34;&gt;doi:10.1145/1232919.1232926&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bobbriscoe.net/pubs.html#rateFairDis&#34;&gt;Author&amp;rsquo;s listing of paper and slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;novel-idea-main-result-s&#34;&gt;Novel Idea / Main Result(s)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main claim of the paper is that flow rate as a metric for fairness is completely bogus and a better metric for the same should be the cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;impact&#34;&gt;Impact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not completely sure how fairness criterion has/has not changed in the past 10 years since this paper was published. But my takeaway from this paper is that long-established norms should not be taken for granted and there is value in evaluating the truth for each established view from time to time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s fair to say though that I did not find any rebuttal paper in the defense of flow rate fairness as the author of this paper demands. However, RFC 5290 presents some alternate views on the topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;evidence&#34;&gt;Evidence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not find the argument very convincing given the lack of analytical or empirical analysis. The reasoning is based on arguments from philosophy, social science and &amp;ldquo;real life&amp;rdquo; for a more accurate definition of fairness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reproducibility&#34;&gt;Reproducibility&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, the description is not sufficient to reproduce the work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;question&#34;&gt;Question&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was reminded of thinking about the Internet as a utility (from the net neutrality debate outside of this paper) and how another utility &amp;ndash; electricity &amp;ndash; is well distributed across the grid system fairly. I wonder if there are lessons to be learned from this analogy given the complexities and non-uniform nature of the global Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;criticism&#34;&gt;Criticism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My main concern with this paper is that it tries to make such a big claim about the futility of a fairness metric that has been working for a couple of decades but fails to provide enough persuasive evidence to substantiate the claims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ideas-for-further-work&#34;&gt;Ideas for further work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See the Question section above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Review Template Credits:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://cs.brown.edu/courses/csci2950-u/s14/review.html&#34;&gt;Prof. Rodrigo Fonseca&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis and Simulation of a Fair Queueing Algorithm</title>
      <link>https://techglider.github.io/review/analysis-and-simulation-of-a-fair-queueing-algorithm/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2017 07:12:31 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://techglider.github.io/review/analysis-and-simulation-of-a-fair-queueing-algorithm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;paper-title&#34;&gt;Paper Title&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Analysis and Simulation of a Fair Queueing Algorithm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;author-s&#34;&gt;Author(s)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alan Demers, Srinivasan Keshav and Scott Shenker&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;date&#34;&gt;Date&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;September 1989. Symposium proceedings on Communications architectures &amp;amp; protocols (SIGCOMM &amp;lsquo;89).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;doi-authoritative-link-to-paper&#34;&gt;DOI/Authoritative Link to Paper&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1145/75246.75248&#34;&gt;doi:10.1145/75246.75248&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cseweb.ucsd.edu/classes/wi01/cse222/papers/demers-fq-ire90.pdf&#34;&gt;Alternate single column format&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;novel-idea-main-result-s&#34;&gt;Novel Idea / Main Result(s)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper presents an improved version of the fair queueing algorithm first proposed by Nagle, discusses limitations of congestion control with FCFS queuing, presents mathematical foundation behind their algorithm and finally, discusses the performance of this new algorithm in various real world scenarios with the help of simulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;impact&#34;&gt;Impact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the first time that performance implications of a fair queuing algorithm were studied in detail and published. Network scheduling / queue management became an active area of networks research with several other algorithms proposed later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, this paper identifies flow (called conversations in this paper) as a good criterion for bandwidth &amp;amp; buffer allocations, which has become a standard concept in the Software-Defined Networking research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;evidence&#34;&gt;Evidence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors come up with a methodology to emulate bit-wise round robin scheduling (which is intuitive to fairness but impractical for implementation) and provide both rigorous mathematical analysis and empirical analysis (with the help of network simulation experiments in various scenario) to justify their results. The evidence is, hence, quite convincing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reproducibility&#34;&gt;Reproducibility&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, the description is enough, with a lot of work and resources&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;question&#34;&gt;Question&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Primarily, I wonder, (as the authors point out in conclusion) whether technology has matured enough in past 30 years that we can have a true implementation of a fair queuing (for a reasonable definition of &amp;ldquo;fair&amp;rdquo;)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;criticism&#34;&gt;Criticism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found the mathematics covered in ยง2.3 fairly hard to follow and perhaps it could have used further explanation. This is in contrast to the scenario diagrams presented in a later section which were both self-descriptive and had major observations pointed out in prose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ideas-for-further-work&#34;&gt;Ideas for further work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NA&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Review Template Credits:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://cs.brown.edu/courses/csci2950-u/s14/review.html&#34;&gt;Prof. Rodrigo Fonseca&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Congestion Avoidance and Control</title>
      <link>https://techglider.github.io/review/congestion-avoidance-and-control/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2017 22:43:36 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://techglider.github.io/review/congestion-avoidance-and-control/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;paper-title&#34;&gt;Paper Title&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congestion Avoidance and Control&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;author-s&#34;&gt;Author(s)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Van Jacobson and Michael J Karels&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;date&#34;&gt;Date&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;November 1988 (Slightly revised version; originally published in Symposium proceedings on Communications architectures and protocols (SIGCOMM &amp;lsquo;88))&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;doi-authoritative-link-to-paper&#34;&gt;DOI/Authoritative Link to Paper&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1145/52324.52356&#34;&gt;doi:10.1145/52324.52356&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cs.princeton.edu/courses/archive/fall06/cos561/papers/tcp.pdf&#34;&gt;Revised version that I read&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;novel-idea-main-result-s&#34;&gt;Novel Idea / Main Result(s)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper describes the congestion-related problems observed in the erstwhile TCP variant and reports on the algorithms introduced to tackle those problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;impact&#34;&gt;Impact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given we are still reading/talking about this paper after almost three decades, it is fair to say the paper has had a lasting impact. Recalling the congestion control and avoidance concepts studied in &lt;a href=&#34;https://cs.brown.edu/courses/csci1680/f16/&#34;&gt;CS168&lt;/a&gt;, I see that most of those basic ideas originated here in this paper and its references.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;evidence&#34;&gt;Evidence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both intuitive/mathematical and empirical analysis is described. I especially like the effectiveness of the diagrams in Fig 1 and 2. The charts are all drawn from experiments done between LBL and UCB in a real setting and hence are quite convincing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reproducibility&#34;&gt;Reproducibility&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, the description is enough, with a lot of work and resources&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;question&#34;&gt;Question&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors talk about possible change in some of their results when the Internet grows large (like the introduction of a third term in the Taylor series on pg. 9) at multiple points. I would like to see what all has changed and what has stood the test of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;criticism&#34;&gt;Criticism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NA&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ideas-for-further-work&#34;&gt;Ideas for further work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found the connections to queueing theory/control theory and even the conservation principle of liquid flow as an analogy to network flow really interesting. It also reminded me of &lt;a href=&#34;https://techglider.github.io/review/time-clocks-and-ordering-of-events-in-a-distributed-system/&#34;&gt;Lamport&amp;rsquo;s time, clocks, ordering paper&lt;/a&gt; where he was able to bring in ideas from relativity into computing. These connections, in general, suggest how sometimes well-established ideas from another field can be applied to one&amp;rsquo;s field and why interdisciplinary research makes good sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Review Template Credits:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://cs.brown.edu/courses/csci2950-u/s14/review.html&#34;&gt;Prof. Rodrigo Fonseca&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;note&#34;&gt;Note&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am taking a graduate seminar this semester at Brown: &lt;a href=&#34;http://cs.brown.edu/courses/csci2950-u/s17/&#34;&gt;Special Topics on Networking and Distributed Systems&lt;/a&gt;. This and most of the following paper reviews until early-May will be my reviews submitted for this seminar with some minor editing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This review posted here on Feb 9, 2017&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>